Host: sitting in a room in the basement of a building in central London with an Oxford academic who's an expert on war.
Games Master: So my name's Dr Rob Johnson.
Games Master: My area of research is about decision -making in crises and in conflicts.
Host: Rob Johnson is showing me a piece of his own family's wartime history. It's something he always keeps with him.
Games Master: In front of me I've got my grandpa, this pocket watch, which he carried during the battle in Atlantic and the battle in the Mediterranean at Malta.
Games Master: And this pocket watch was going to my father and subsequently to me.
Host: Reginald Johnson had been a Shakespearean actor before the Second World War broke out.
Host: Like most of his generation, he put his own dreams on hold
Host: serve the nation in its time of crisis.
Host: His grandson though has dedicated his whole life to defence
Host: a soldier, a scholar and a senior civil servant.
Host: Rob is fiercely loyal to his country
Host: would never want to talk it down.
Host: But he's become increasingly worried about the state of the UK's defences after a prolonged period of peace
Host: seen the government and society
Host: what it means to be ready for war.
Host: a concern he raised while seconded to the Ministry of Defence.
Games Master: job was to try to alert colleagues to what was going on and where the gaps were.
Games Master: What I found actually was that many, many people agreed with me. They knew where in the position we are.
Games Master: But the response often was,
Games Master: look, government's match choice and the government of the day and the governments we've had have all made the same choice, which is that we're going to invest in health and education and roads and growth, not in defence.
Host: Resilience was second nature during the Cold War, but when the Soviet Union collapsed, successive Prime Ministers spent less on the armed forces and more on other priorities.
Host: European allies did the same, all seeing this as a peace dividend, while gambling that the United States would still protect them if things went wrong.
Host: the threat posed by Russia never really went away
Host: now under Donald Trump,
Host: America's support to its partners in NATO no longer feels so guaranteed.
Guest: think it's common sense, right?
Guest: If they don't pay, I'm not going to defend them now, I'm not going to defend them.
Guest: got into a lot of heat
Guest: I said that. You said, oh, he's violating NATO.
Host: Europe weak and Russia on a war footing,
Host: it's a perfect storm.
Host: I'm Debra Haines, the security and defence editor at Sky News.
Host: been a journalist for the past two and a half decades and can tell you that Rob isn't alone with his concerns.
Host: much everyone I speak to inside the military says the UK has allowed its defences to shrink too far
Host: has lost the kind of national resilience it once had during the Cold War.
Host: because we live in a country that generally feels pretty safe,
Host: it's perhaps hard to understand why or even whether that matters.
Host: may be wonder what if we simulate an emergency and find out how the UK might respond.
Host: the outcome,
Host: it would at least bring to life the reality of the threat.
Host: year I got in touch with Rob,
Host: who's out of government service now
Host: back in his day job
Host: the head of the changing character of Warcenter at Oxford University.
Host: asked him if he might be up for running a war game
Host: an attack on the UK
Host: former ministers and military chiefs
Host: the part of the British side.
Host: thought it was worth a try.
Host: It's why we're sitting together in this basement.
Games Master: we chose a bunker.
Games Master: We've created some maps. Then I looked at
Host: Rob's just finalising the game he's devised over the past few months.
Games Master: So we've got a lot of mechanics we've had to put together behind the game. It's taken a long time.
Games Master: So it did a bit of research.
Host: He describes the scenario as extremely low likelihood but high impact.
Host: means a low chance of it happening
Host: catastrophic consequences if it did.
Host: And as he works on a desk in front of him,
Host: it's his grandfather's watch.
Games Master: pretty dramatic because you can hear the ticking of this clock and it feels like both in the game but also for real that our time is running out.
Host: you're about to hear is the kind of war game that's genuinely tested inside government.
Host: main difference
Host: that nothing discussed in Rob's version is classified.
Host: knows our weaknesses.
Host: do you?
Host: Sky News and Tortoise,
Host: this is The War Game.
Host: Episode 1, False Flag.
Chief of the General Staff
Defence Secretary: can you hear me through the mic on that? I'm hearing that camera this way. Perfect.
National Security Advisor
Host
Games Master: Okay, I think we're all set.
Games Master
National Security Advisor: Thank you.
National Security Advisor
National Security Advisor: Well,
Games Master: first of all, thank you very much indeed. All of you for the hours you're giving up the time.
Host: is welcoming his players into the basement.
Host: been transformed into the set of The War Game
Host: three rooms connected by a winding corridor.
Host: one has a table, some chairs, and a network of microphones to record every conversation.
Games Master: Thank you so much. I've got my Pembroke College students at the back from Oxford. Thanks so much for coming. They helped with all the rehearsals.
Host: the game's master,
Host: he heads what's known as the White Cell, which runs the event.
Games Master: the crew of individuals at the back here.
Host: Rob has a team of helpers who give the various participants certain slips of paper containing new information at different times throughout the game.
Host: in War Game language are known as Injects.
Host: let me bring in the players.
Home Secretary: you, you have a section. I was judged by the secretary, your secretary.
National Security Advisor: So this is all my yesterday.
Home Secretary
Prime Minister
Foreign Secretary
Prime Minister: of our yesterday. Let's be honest.
Host: games typically have a blue team and a red team.
Host: In our scenario,
Host: blue is an imagined British government,
Host: red is a fictional Kremlin.
Host: chose our cast carefully, ensuring a mix of labour and conservative ministers and top officials who either played the roles they've been given for real or have deep expertise in different but relevant jobs.
Prime Minister: Ben Wallace, former Secretary of State Feds, and I'm going to be playing the Prime Minister of the United Kingdom.
Host: Why do you want to take part in this?
Prime Minister: Because I think it's really important that we demonstrate to the public how government makes decisions in real crisis and emergencies. And it's at that moment in time that no matter what people's party politics are, people pulled together for the right reasons.
Host: the War Game, Ben heads across party government
Host: at a time of heightened tensions with Vladimir Putin's Russia.
Prime Minister: think what's amazing about this, the team you put together devs, is
Prime Minister: all the real deal. I mean, I'm not the Prime Minister, but we've all been
Prime Minister: and I think that's quite unique, to be honest.
Host: let him and his team introduce themselves.
Prime Minister: After myself as Prime Minister, which is an interesting choice, I'm going to look forward to it. I've got Jack Straw.
Foreign Secretary: Jack Straw, home secretary between 1997 and 2001, foreign secretary between 2001 and 2006, and justice secretary between 2007 and 2010.
Prime Minister: He's very experienced.
Foreign Secretary: And I'm playing the role of foreign secretary.
Prime Minister: got Amber Rudd, my former boss when I was security minister in the home office.
Home Secretary: Amber Rudd, former secretary of state for energy and climate change 2015 to 2016, and then home secretary 2016 to 2018.
Prime Minister
Prime Minister: She is going to be doing the part of the home secretary. And then I've got my former colleague,
Defence Secretary: James Hepe. James Hepe, I was minister for the Armed Forces from 2019 to 2024 and I'm playing the defence secretary.
Defence Secretary
Prime Minister: one of the most experienced
Prime Minister: parliamentarians who had done tours in Northern Ireland and Iraq and Afghanistan as a soldier in some very difficult times. I've got Baroness Kennedy as our attorney general.
Prime Minister
Attorney General: Hello, Nick Kennedy. I'm a member of the House of Lords. I'm a practitioner barrister, King's council of lengthy experience. And I know practice in international law, international humanitarian law and laws of war.
Prime Minister: Kennedy is a great campaigner on human rights and international law and she will keep us on the legal, straight and narrow. And then another colleague I work with, Lord Sedwell.
National Security Advisor: Mark Sedwell, national security adviser 2017 to 20, cabinet secretary 2018 to 20, former permanent secretary of the
Prime Minister: office, former ambassador in Afghanistan,
Prime Minister: and national security adviser.
Prime Minister: And national security adviser in the exercise.
Prime Minister: chief of defence staff is general
Chief of the Defence Staff: barons. General Sir Richard Barons, I come on to joint forces, come on to 2013 to 2016 and I've just finished being one of the leaders of the 2025 defence review. Just
Prime Minister: hot on the heels of delivering Labour's current strategic defence review even innovative and forward -thinking general, so that is going to be really great.
Host: also have a chancellor who you'll meet in episode two.
Games Master: And the scenarios they're flying in from Beijing.
Prime Minister: The treasury are playing their role perfectly as ever.
Games Master
Defence Secretary
Prime Minister: It's not a joke, they often wouldn't attend meetings.
Defence Secretary: It's very normal for the treasury to miss Cobra.
Host: Finally, the prime minister has a press secretary who's played by Victoria Maconess.
Attorney General: Victoria Maconess, I'm a communications specialist.
Host: She's a former civil servant and an expert on communications who works in the defence industry.
Host: Ben Wallace and his government are being supported by a group of expert advisers who you'll hear more from later.
Host: We'll also meet the Russia team once the game is underway.
Host: Governments around the world use war games to run through scenarios and test responses for literally anything from health emergencies to World War III.
Host: Typically, they're conducted in secret, with the blue and the red teams pitched against each other, each able to act as they choose.
Host: our scenario though, the red team, while free to make some choices, is already aware of the key steps it will take.
Host: contrast, the blue team knows very little about the scenario
Host: will have to respond to whatever comes its way.
Host: well as running the show,
Host: Rob is playing the role of what's known as the chair of the Joint Intelligence Committee, or Jic -Cher.
Host: Heal share updates from the UK spy agencies, MI6, MI5 and GCHQ, as well as defence intelligence, which is part of the Ministry of Defence, or MOD.
Host: are lots of acronyms in the military and the security world. I'll try to spell them out whenever they come up.
Host: With the drama about to start, Ben and his team have assembled around a long table in the largest of the basement rooms.
Games Master
Host: the real world, it's a Tuesday morning in early April.
Host: In the war game,
Host: it's almost six months in the future,
Host: the government is in crisis mode.
Host: set the scene, we've mocked up some rolling news reports from an imagined UK television station.
Host: Everyone stops talking
Host: listens.
News Reader
News Reader: It's 8am on Monday 29th September, our top story this morning. Travel chaos on the railways and the roads after a major power cut left parts of England and Wales without electricity.
News Reader: Multiple train stations have been forced to close to passengers this morning after what the National Grid is describing as an issue with two generators.
News Reader: Reports are also coming in of problems on the roads. Transport for London says some traffic lights in the capital are out of action and police officers may be called in to manage certain junctions.
News Reader: disruption comes just three days after simultaneous fires broke out at ferry terminals in Plymouth and Portsmouth, halting channel ferry crossings over the weekend.
News Reader: The Home Office says counterterrorism officers are now investigating the fires as a precautionary measure.
News Reader: The security sources say they haven't ruled out foul play.
News Reader: year the heads of MI6 and the CIA accused Moscow of waging a reckless campaign of sabotage across Europe.
Host
Host: Russia has previously denied involvement in any sabotage attacks and the could of course be a perfectly innocent explanation for this transport chaos.
Host: For now, the cause is unclear.
Host: Then,
Host: two days later,
Host: happens.
Host
News Reader: 8 a .m. on Wednesday, the 1st of October.
News Reader: Our top story. Explosions have ripped through a major naval base in Northern Russia killing and wounding dozens of personnel.
News Reader: Russian President has suggested the attack at Severo Morse was linked to the UK and has vowed revenge.
News Reader: British government has yet to comment, but downing street sources have strongly rejected the allegation of any UK involvement.
News Reader: bring you more as we get it.
Host: tensions grow between Moscow and London over the next few days,
Host: British police make a shocking discovery.
News Reader: It's 4 p .m. on Sunday, the 5th of October. Our top story. The Ministry of Defence says two F -35 pilots have been found shot dead in Norfolk. The circumstances of the deaths are not clear and military police are investigating.
News Reader: Both pilots are part of 617 Squadron, which fly the UK's most sophisticated F -35 warplanes out of RAF Marum.
News Reader: other news, Moscow has recalled its ambassador to London saying Britain is now considered an unfriendly state.
News Reader: extraordinary move follows the deadly blasts at a major Russian naval base that the Kremlin has claimed were linked to the UK,
News Reader: but without providing evidence.
Host: mysterious killing of two such elite fighter pilots coupled with the aggressive rhetoric from Moscow
Host: the Prime Minister to convene an emergency Cobra meeting.
Host: are held at times of crisis.
Host: Cobra stands for Cabinet Office Briefing Rooms.
Host: wargame begins at 5 p .m. on Sunday, the 5th of October, 2025.
Prime Minister: called this after the deaths of the two F -35 pilots coupled with the growing both intelligence and situation with Britain being put at the heart of the messaging from Russia. So, thank you colleagues for attending it on Sunday afternoon. Could I ask the National Security Adviser Mar -Sendwell to honour through the agenda?
National Security Advisor: Prime Minister, thanks. I suggest we start just by saying whether there's anything further in terms of threat or other intelligence that we need to know before we come to
National Security Advisor: various options for action both by you and colleagues.
Host: gives his first injective information to the players.
Games Master: I'll start with the situation updates of where we are.
Games Master: There was indeed on the 1st of October a terrorist attack in Northern Russia.
Games Master: does appear that the early hours of that day, over a hundred Russian naval personnel were killed, in detonations around the port of Murmansk, several moresks, and its residential area. GCSQ did a lot of work to try and identify who had been behind this particular attack, rather curiously there were some inferences that Dagestan has involved.
Host: intelligence is referring to Islamist extremists from the Russian Republic of Dagestan.
Host: suggests their motivation for launching the attack could be anger at Moscow for recruiting their men to fight in Ukraine.
Games Master: Russian government announced
Games Master: they needed little further evidence to confirm that this wasn't attacked by British intelligence using divers. I think we can dismiss this nonsense.
Host: Rob then shares information from MI5 on the two F -35 pilots whose bodies were found early in the morning.
Games Master: the pit have died on Saturday night.
Games Master: Police investigations are ongoing.
Games Master: We have low confidence in the intelligence so far,
Games Master: but it's likely that these men were tracked before they were killed.
Host: highlights two other important developments.
Games Master: Signal's intelligence reveals that there is a snap Russian naval exercise underway today, involving rehearsals to the deployment of surface surface missiles and North Atlantic.
Games Master: they also note that Cheltenham is the intensity of cyber attacks on UK businesses and government websites has increased by a magnitude of 65%.
Host: refers to the location of GCHQ,
Host: the government signals and cyber intelligence agency.
Host: the cause of the rise in cyber attacks isn't clear,
Host: it could be yet another sign of hostile Russian activity.
Host: National Security Advisor is interested in what appears to be an exceptionally large Russian naval exercise, involving warships, aircraft and submarines.
Host: It's being tracked by American Norwegian and British ships.
Host: he says CDS, he means Chief of the Defence Staff.
Host: That's the Prime Minister's top military adviser and head of the UK Armed Forces.
National Security Advisor: perhaps from CDS, just more on the Russian naval exercise and how we're monitoring it. In particular, CDS, do you have any concerns about how they're operating in these circumstances?
Chief of the Defence Staff: Yes, thank you. Prime Minister, if I may, from the military perspective, I'd like to widen this discussion a little bit. I think it's becoming clear that the country is being subject to a wide range of coercion.
Chief of the Defence Staff: We've seen the attacks on the railway,
Chief of the Defence Staff: the likely attacks on the traffic infrastructure in London and the ferry fires, and now we have had two F -35 pilots murdered.
Chief of the Defence Staff: I have to say that if we fit all of those things together, the murder of the pilots is a traditional special forces activity. So we should not indulge ourselves by thinking that was some sort of accident.
Host: pilots was part of the Soviet playbook during the Cold War.
Host: Richard Barons, the general who's playing our defence chief,
Host: once told me about a Czech Special Forces officer,
Host
Host: whose task in the run up to war once he'd smuggled himself into the UK,
Host: would have been to go to the officer's mess at an RAF base in Lincolnshire on a Friday night during happy hour and shoot all the pilots.
Host: when you think about it, a 9mm bullet is a much more efficient way of grounding an air force than a barrage of missiles.
Chief of the Defence Staff: So what I've done so far is I have made sure that all the pilots of our F -35 and Typhoon aircraft are now coming into their bases and they will stay there with their families until
Chief of the Defence Staff: situation is clearer.
Host: means they'll have additional security.
Chief of the Defence Staff: answer the National Security Adviser's direct question, we are monitoring a Russian exercise in the North Atlantic.
Chief of the Defence Staff: The two dimensions to this, one is as reported the Russian nuclear
Chief of the Defence Staff: bomber submarines are coming into the Atlantic. Now they could threaten the UK from anywhere in the Atlantic.
Chief of the Defence Staff: the two other submarines that carry cruise missiles could threaten the UK with conventional attack from certainly the eastern half of the Atlantic. So my concern as CDS now is that we are in the managing a great deal of Russian coercion.
Chief of the Defence Staff: We can't exclude that we're on the threshold of this becoming a military attack of the UK, this might all be precursor activity. And I need to get the armed forces ready for that. Without, of course, provoking Russia into the one activity we would wish them to avoid. So I'm going to ask that we begin to concentrate some of the military units in their bases and I may even dispose them. I need to start out learning some supplies so that we're not caught short.
Host: talking about ordering troops to their barracks, potentially getting them to spread out to other sites and
Host: ensuring things like ammunition, fuel and other supplies are brought out of storage.
National Security Advisor: if I may, I think we have to assume that essentially we're now being put to the test. There's a series of unconventional activities by the Russians. We mustn't jump to conclusions, we certainly mustn't say that publicly. But potentially arson attacks, possibly these two assassinations, not a believer in coincidence. And now we have them essentially raising readiness in terms of the deployment of their naval forces.
National Security Advisor
Host: many around the table,
Host: he's encountered Russian aggression before.
Host: Mark said well was the real national security adviser
Host: the UK accused Vladimir Putin's Russia of attempting to kill the former Russian double agent Sergey Skripal
Host: his daughter, Yulia,
Host: with a novichok nerve agent in Sozbri in 2018.
Host: Moscow has always denied involvement.
Host: Mark led efforts alongside Amber Rudd as the home secretary and Ben Wallace, a security minister at the time,
Host: to rally NATO allies to retaliate to the attack.
Host: had left the Skripals critically ill
Host: killed a British woman, Dawn Sturgis.
Host: More than 20 nations agreed to a mass expulsion of alleged Russian spies from their respective countries.
National Security Advisor: And I suspect what they're doing, as Putin always does,
National Security Advisor: challenging the old Leninist doctrine, keep pushing. And if you meet steel retreat, if you meet mush keep going. And so I think
National Security Advisor: is putting us and NATO to the test. And we should work on the assumption that this will continue until unless we respond. I think the discussion PM if I may suggest should take place in that context.
Prime Minister: Okay, good.
Host: Russia, the reporting of the attack on the naval base has a very different spin.
Host: asked an expert on Russian state communications, Valery Akimenko, to help us craft and imagine state media bulletin.
Russian News Reader
Russian News Reader: frogman's outfit has been discovered on the beach near the Severamorsk naval base.
Russian News Reader: The head of the investigation into last Wednesday's attack
Russian News Reader: this is powerful evidence of British involvement in the terrorist atrocity.
Russian News Reader: Several experts have likened this suspected British operation
Russian News Reader: the Nazi surprise attack on the Soviet Union in 1941.
Russian News Reader: It is just the latest example of a British -sponsored terrorism.
Russian News Reader: As you know, the UK has been the closest backer of the Nazi regime in Ukraine.
President of Russia: I'm Kyrgyzstan, I study and explain Russia for a living. I have written a number of books about what Russia does, why it does it and what it's going to do next.
President of Russia: I'm playing the president of Russia in this war game.
Host: Kremlin for the purpose of the game is in another room separated from the British side by a corridor, a hall and a couple of doors.
Host: Kyrgyz joined by three other experts, each with experience of playing the Russia side in war games to help Western allies better understand the threat posed by Moscow.
President of Russia: There's Tom Sarostok's from Latvia, who is going to be playing the Chief of the General Staff, so in charge of the Russian military.
Host: In real life, Tom's is a director of the National Defence Academy of Latvia.
Host: He's flown to London especially for the war game.
Chief of the General Staff: It's October in the game. This may go down in history as the British missile crisis.
Head of Military Intelligence: It also luckily coincides with the birth date of our
Head of Military Intelligence: leader and president.
Host: Also, just off of flight is Maria Engvist,
Host: deputy head of the Russia and Eurasia Studies programme at the Swedish Defence Research Agency.
President of Russia: going to be playing the head of military intelligence.
Host: Yeah, sevens of October,
Head of Military Intelligence
President of Russia: if I
Head of Military Intelligence: do not remember in Kremlin.
Host: Known as the GRU, this is the agency that the UK believes carried out the Solzby spy poisonings and many other hostile acts.
President of Russia: And then dining in remotely we have Robin Huggblum. He is a naval analyst from Finland and he will be playing the commander of Russia's Northern Fleet.
Commander of Russia's Northern Fleet: Navy is very eager to take this opportunity to be able to extract revenge for the terrorist attack at Severo Mars.
Host: Appearing via video link,
Host: his backdrop shows the inside of a warship.
President of Russia: got a good backdrop.
President of Russia: Robin looks very operational.
Host: reality, he's in his office in Finland.
Host: Robin is a senior adviser at a risk assessment company called Risk Intelligence.
Host: despite what he said
Host: extracting revenge,
Host: no one on the Russian team really believes the UK had anything to do with the explosions at their naval base.
Chief of the General Staff: is our assessment that it was the terrorist attack carried out by Dagestani extremists.
Host: Chief of the General Staff has just been asked who was responsible.
Host: too, blames Dagestani militants,
Host: echoing the British assessment.
President of Russia: good. Thank you, colleagues. I approve of your assessment. We will deal with our Dagestani terrorists at another time,
President of Russia: but this provides a historic opportunity to neutralize the Anglo -Saxons as an obstacle to our objectives.
President of Russia: agree with your recommendation that we should use the Severo Marska attack as a pretext for launching Operation Tuman.
Host: is the secret code name the Russian side has given its attack plan.
Host: word means fog in Russian.
Host: president asks his spy chief whether she thinks the US will help the UK.
Head of Military Intelligence: It is the assessment of my agency that the US have no interest in engaging in war fighting in Europe. Britain and the US have drifted apart increasingly during the past years. US resources remain focused in the end of the Pacific. This is a bold and necessary operation that will effectively be the end of NATO.
Host: commander of the Northern Fleet gives an update on the readiness of his fortilla.
Commander of Russia's Northern Fleet: As we have been able to prepare for these strikes for two months,
Commander of Russia's Northern Fleet: are in a relatively good shape. Though, of course, we have not been able to create any miracles or new units to deplete in this time.
President of Russia: So, to confirm Admiral, we are not expecting that the United Kingdom is able to defend realistically against our missiles. Is that correct?
Commander of Russia's Northern Fleet: That is correct.
Commander of Russia's Northern Fleet: The number of end defenses they have available able to intercept our missiles is very limited. We have a significant number of missiles aboard our ships and submarines. This should not be an issue.
Host: has identified a glaring vulnerability here that as with most of Britain's military cuts can be traced back to the end of the Cold War, when successive governments ran down their ability to defeat attacks from the sky to save cash.
Host: Today, only a handful of RAF squadrons and a limited number of army systems can intercept cruise missiles.
Host: are self -guided weapons propelled by a jet engine that are powered all the way onto a target.
Host: for ballistic missiles, which are blasted to a high altitude, even out of the Earth's atmosphere, before dropping at a steep angle onto a target at great speed,
Host: Royal Navy's Type -45 Destroyers are the UK's sole line of defense.
Host: it only has six of these billion -pound warships and four are routinely unavailable because of maintenance woes and crew shortages.
Host: of them,
Host: HMS Daring,
Host: has spent more years being fixed than out at sea.
Host: NATO command base in Germany is responsible for defending the airspace of the whole alliance, including the UK.
Host: However, British forces would be the first line of defense against any threats coming straight at them from the Atlantic.
President of Russia: of General Staff,
President of Russia: I would like to hear from you about our overall military position.
Host: President is now asking his defence chief about the overall state of Russia's armed forces given their war in Ukraine.
Chief of the General Staff: course, much attention has been paid in past years on the
Chief of the General Staff: military operation and the losses that we have suffered during that operation.
Chief of the General Staff: And those losses have been significant. However, in terms of military personnel,
Chief of the General Staff: we have recovered,
Chief of the General Staff: our military
Chief of the General Staff: the coming years will be even larger than it was before the start of the special military operation.
Chief of the General Staff: So for a target like the United Kingdom,
Chief of the General Staff: we are in as strong a position as we were before.
Chief of the General Staff: Yes, and we are certainly in a stronger position than the UK.
Chief of the General Staff: Thank you for your assessment.
Host: in London, Amber Rudd, playing the home secretary, has an update for the Cobra meeting. I'm so sorry,
Home Secretary: I've got some urgent news Prime Minister, so I feel it ought to be on the table, that we've heard from my five Russian families are leaving the UK.
Home Secretary: And that includes diplomatic staff.
Host
Prime Minister
Guest
Home Secretary: I mean, I would suggest that I'll meet it in query, I would turn it this day, to find out from Dick whether we have any further intelligence from
Home Secretary: perhaps who might know more about some intentions. But the fact that Russian staff are leaving at speed is... Do we have any reports
Prime Minister: of the activity of the Russian intelligence officers
Home Secretary
Prime Minister: the embassy? And do we see any activity of Russians, G -I -U or whatever, in the UK has that changed?
Home Secretary: I think I'd ask Jack Cher about that, family. We'll
Games Master: put on that under immediate investigation, Prime Minister.
Prime Minister
Host: exodus of a number of Russian families is a further indicator that something bad is heading the UK's way.
Home Secretary: As the CDS said in his earlier remarks, this is an escalation of the squeeze we've felt from the Russians in terms of their attacks on the UK and on other European countries as well. Do you have any of you promised, or perhaps the foreign sector, about what the Russians arrived, what are they trying to achieve? Is it anything in particular, or is it just a retaliation for an event that took place that we weren't in fact responsible for, but they want to show a response to?
Prime Minister: One of the challenges is Russia has a long track record of force flag
Home Secretary: for
Prime Minister: the purpose of its own agenda.
Host: false flag can mean an action like a bombing or an assassination
Host: that's done by one side but blamed on the other to create a fake pretext to attack them.
Host: Attribution is also typically hard, making it difficult for the accused to prove their innocence.
Host: this case, the Russian government did not deliberately target its own naval base, but it knows who did, yet the Kremlin is using the atrocity as a way to falsely smear the British and excuse whatever activity it plans to do next.
Prime Minister: saw that in the build up of the Ukraine war, which was exposed by the West on a number of occasions, and so there is almost nothing ever off limit with the Russians in how they currently function.
Host
Host: He should know,
Host: Ben Wallace was the UK's real defence secretary,
Host: he was a leading voice in 2021,
Host: raising the alarm about the impending threat of a Russian invasion of Ukraine.
Host: was also instrumental in rushing out British weapons to Ukrainian forces
Host: help them fend off the initial onslaught the following year.
Prime Minister
Prime Minister: We were in one summer, they were determined that the British and others were behind a dirty bomb,
Prime Minister: totally untrue and false, and to this day I would still be guessing whether they believed it or whether they made it up themselves. So I think we can only really look at their physical deployment as the marker and trying to undo the riddle
Prime Minister: be a lot of energy, you know, the riddle behind it all.
Host: Helena Kennedy, as the attorney general, offers her view.
Attorney General: could be testing whether the NATO alliance is actually as solid as it once was, and we know that that fragility is one of the issues that concerns us, and they may be actually putting that to the test. Always
Prime Minister: punching the brews.
Attorney General
Prime Minister
Host: Suddenly, the chair of the Joint Intelligence Committee interrupts.
Games Master: we've just hired two injects, one from Defence Intelligence, which is also replicated from the information coming from SIS.
Host: SIS is another acronym for MI6, it means Secret Intelligence Service.
Host: Rob reveals that more submarines have joined the Russian flattilla in the North Atlantic.
Games Master: we estimate the total now out of Severamorsk is seven SSBNs, which is the entire Northern Fleet Bar one, eight SSNs.
Games Master
Prime Minister: Just for clarity, SSBN is the bombers and SSN are the hunter killer submarines. That's correct. That's 15 submarines in the North Atlantic.
National Security Advisor: Well, 1pm clustered. That's the very striking.
Host: screen in the cobra room lights up with a map that shows the Russian deployment also includes two large destroyers and four frigates.
Host: are medium sized ships armed with missiles.
Host: Such a formidable display of naval power is the biggest warning sign yet from Moscow.
Games Master: is a well above the normal compliments that we would expect to see deployed.
Games Master: all assembled at a rendezvous point that you can see from our map that they are moving in a southwestern
Games Master: And there are active Russian air operations over the North Atlantic, all of which are being tracked by our own surveillance sites and by our own surveillance aircraft and by American satellites. Put in perspective
Prime Minister: for others around the table. Normally, roughly, you'd get
Prime Minister: to five submarines lurking around the Atlantic, Russian, American, French, British.
Guest
Prime Minister: To have 15 from just one power alone is extraordinary and
Prime Minister: takes a huge amount of effort actually by any country to put to see that many submarines. So it is definitely out of the ordinary. I don't
National Security Advisor: know whether the CDS you would have viewed. If you were sitting
National Security Advisor: your Russian counterparts' chair,
National Security Advisor: would the basis would be for deploying not only that number but in that concentration?
Chief of the Defence Staff: So in my view, this is clearly an enormous show of force.
Chief of the Defence Staff: quite out of any form of normal pattern. All of this activity is in international waters and airspace, so it's still at some distance but also protected by international law. It is heading around to the UK, but it remains in range of the UK.
Chief of the Defence Staff: The best outcome is that this is just a show of force. The worst outcome is this is setting a force in order to attack the UK.
Host: National Security Advisor explains this is not just a problem for the UK.
Host: It's a challenge to the whole of the NATO alliance.
Host: 32 member states share responsibility for defending their land, seas and skies.
National Security Advisor: are NATO protocols for this, and
National Security Advisor: obviously anxious in the current circumstances that those protocols might not apply,
National Security Advisor: but if we can just at least test by presuming
National Security Advisor: they will, do it on the perhaps on the professional military channel
National Security Advisor: CDS perhaps, and just
National Security Advisor: presume that they're going to operate as we've always understood they will, and then if it looks as though they won't, we then escalate to the political level.
Host: He's referring here to uncertainty about the United States commitment to defending Europe.
Host: Jack Straw, speaking as the Foreign Secretary, is far more blunt.
Foreign Secretary: Minister, the elephant in the room here is what the US is going to do. In the past, we were confident that the US would be with us.
Foreign Secretary: Now, the question I raised is, as well as quote, sitting in the phone
Foreign Secretary: professional opposite numbers in NATO headquarters and command centres,
Foreign Secretary: we
Foreign Secretary: hit the phones, in my case, to talk to
Foreign Secretary: American Secretary of State? Because if we are able to get a situation where the US understands that this is a threat against them,
Foreign Secretary: well as against us, then we're in a very, very different position
Guest
Foreign Secretary: be able to deter
Foreign Secretary: from a situation where the Russians can take great comfort from the fact that
Foreign Secretary: United States is simply going to sit on its hands.
Host: recently, it would have been implausible even to contemplate the possibility of the United States not immediately mobilising to help defend the UK in the face of such a show of force by Russia,
Host: so much anymore.
Host: Washington has repeatedly warned its NATO allies to stop relying so heavily on American protection and do more to defend themselves.
Host: the same time, the White House has been seeking to forge better relations with Moscow to the dismay of London and most other Western capitals.
Host: an upending of a security landscape that's been in place since the end of the Second World War.
Prime Minister: think the Prime Minister is actually right to
Prime Minister: start point, really, as with the United States here, and secondly, then NATO. The two bodies we have taken
Prime Minister: for granted, but we have definitely taken, as our guarantor for seven to eight years, I think in this situation, we should absolutely take that for starter.
Host: British side also needs to prepare its own military and society for the possibility of the home front being turned into a war zone.
Host: It's something no Prime Minister has seriously considered or planned for since the 1980s.
National Security Advisor: was just going to suggest PM, because those of us who need to put it into effect need to get out of this room and get those actually... Could we do the
Prime Minister: readiness for assurance?
Prime Minister: Yes, readiness in itself is a deterrence
Prime Minister: people. So if I could start, first of all, with CDS and Defence Secretary
Prime Minister: that. What is our ability to either change our readiness, what ideas do you have to increase our readiness, both at sea land and air?
Prime Minister
Defence Secretary: As CDS said earlier on, he's already advising that forces be concentrated and early steps are taken to mobilise and outload supplies. CDS, do you want to expand on that?
Chief of the Defence Staff: So I suggest that we apply the P8 reconnaissance aircraft that we have,
Chief of the Defence Staff: currently one only, but shortly two type 23 anti -submarine frigates that we can put to sea.
Chief of the Defence Staff
Host: Chief of the Defence Staff, CDS, also says one, if possible, two Royal Navy attack submarines are being deployed to help monitor the Russian Flatilla.
Host: also has plans for one of the UK's two aircraft carriers.
Chief of the Defence Staff: recommend that although it's
Chief of the Defence Staff
Chief of the Defence Staff: not at the highest state of readiness,
Chief of the Defence Staff: that we put the Prince of Wales carrier to sea, I believe I can get eight F -35s on board it,
Chief of the Defence Staff: and we send it into the North Atlantic between the Russian group
Chief of the Defence Staff: the UK. It will take some days to get there.
Host: This October, in the real world, the navy's £3 billion carrier will actually be on the other side of the globe.
Host: warship left Portsmouth back in April on an eight -month deployment to the Indo -Pacific.
Host: accompanied by a Type 45 destroyer, an up to 24 of the UK's F -35 jets,
Host: leaving Britain even less well defended.
Host: the war game though,
Host: we've imagined that the trip was cancelled
Host: escalating tensions with Russia,
Host: so the ships and aircraft are available to fight.
Host: Prime Minister has a recommendation as well.
Prime Minister: Could you also look at readying the second
Prime Minister: Trident SSBN?
Host: He's referring to the UK's nuclear armed submarines.
Prime Minister: Obviously we always have one at sea on patrol,
Prime Minister: and while we know one's a refit and there are three others, I would be grateful of
Prime Minister: look at the readiness of that.
Host: It's the most dramatic move yet by the British side,
Host: underlining the gravity of the crisis.
Host: navy has a fleet of four nuclear armed submarines.
Host: One is always deployed on a rotating basis, providing what's known as the continuous at sea deterrence.
Host: means it's ready to fire nuclear weapons to defend the UK, if given the order.
Host: Preparing to put a second submarine out from its base at Fazlein in Scotland
Host: send a clear signal to Moscow to back off.
Prime Minister: let's not forget that that boat is perfectly possible to operate alongside even if it's not at sea.
Host: He means the submarine can still fire nuclear weapons from its moorings if necessary.
Prime Minister: from the Russian point of view, it'll be viewed as a threat.
Host: for the UK homeland, the defence chief is doing the best he can in coordination with NATO to defend as much as possible.
Chief of the Defence Staff: What I recommend is that we surge the Royal Air Force to produce two 24 hour combat air patrols. One vital piece of guidance I need from you. I can take two areas of the UK on a 24 hour basis. I need to prioritise.
Host: says one has to be the Fazlein submarine base.
Chief of the Defence Staff: You've asked me about the second trident boat. I need to put one of those combat air patrols over Fazlein or the nuclear
Chief of the Defence Staff: architecture will be very vulnerable. And the second one I propose to put over an around London,
Chief of the Defence Staff: it.
Host: a pretty devastating admission.
Host: military chief is saying his Air Force only has the capacity to defend two sights in total across the whole of the UK.
Host: Prime Minister isn't so sure London should be one of them.
Prime Minister: in
Prime Minister: of military vulnerability,
Prime Minister: London the priority
Prime Minister
Prime Minister: was
Prime Minister: attack by Russia.
Prime Minister: That randomly hitting sub -overs of London is not
Prime Minister: to
Prime Minister: deteriorate our capabilities as opposed to putting those patrols somewhere like over the RAF bases of East Anglia.
Chief of the Defence Staff
Prime Minister
Chief of the Defence Staff: pros of that depends how you feel about Whitehall
Chief of the Defence Staff: the centre of government and
Chief of the Defence Staff: everything else that sits in and around the centre of London.
Prime Minister
Prime Minister: Yes to Fazlein,
Prime Minister: second deployment for now, not London,
Prime Minister: but over the key military infrastructures.
Prime Minister: you consider.
Host: James Heapy, our defence secretary, then speaks.
Defence Secretary: It's also worth noting that the activity that CDS describes is a not insignificant outload of UK military resource. And I think that that brings with it two issues. Firstly that we will not be able to deploy that amount of force in secret. Indeed you may not want to deploy it in secret, but we need to think carefully about what the messaging is that we attach to the outload of those forces. But secondly, it won't escape the notice of many in the commentary that what we do deploy is still overmatched by what the Russians have deployed as well.
Host: they talk, another update comes in.
Chief of the Defence Staff: Forgive me, I have one piece of news which is I understand it and a cooler -class Russian submarine has surfaced off Orkney
Chief of the Defence Staff: it's then parallel to commercial ferry
Chief of the Defence Staff: then submerged.
Host: Imagine this.
Host: on a ferry to the Orkney Islands off the north coast of Scotland along with dozens of other passengers.
Host: look out the window and see a giant grey attack submarine pop up out the water and then dive again.
Host: People would surely pull out their phones to take videos and photographs to share online. That
Chief of the Defence Staff: is
Chief of the Defence Staff: exceptional activity, it's clearly threatening and it's messaging to us. It's also public, so we'll not be able to keep that as secret in a way that a Russian deployment in the North Atlantic might be a secret. I mean this
Home Secretary: is clearly breaking out nationally CDS, they've been seen it, but also the fact that the Russian diplomats and their families are leaving is now all over Twitter.
Host: The home secretary.
Home Secretary: it's going to be very evident that the Russians are signaling that there may be, let's call it what it is, so there may be an attack.
Prime Minister: I think we just have to be cautious of the word attack at the moment. We have to
Guest
Prime Minister: ourselves,
Prime Minister: we have to be determined and
Prime Minister: focused, clear messaging of denial. While
Prime Minister: important fish to catch in this phase is a strong US commitment and NATO commitment to this. At the same time, a lot of work in the civil contingency secretary act to make sure we prepare
Guest
Host
Prime Minister: domestic defenses, MI5, police leave, consider whether we cancel police leave, etc, to make sure we can maximize our readiness.
Home Secretary: If I may, I agree with all that, I just think we need to just think how we're going to message the public as this escalates. And I would really like to have, I don't know if you're going to be doing media or the press secretary's going to be doing media, but just some reassuring words, but also acknowledging the threat that we're under. Because that will be available. So, home
Guest
Prime Minister
Prime Minister: secretary, as the guardian of the domestic threat, I would ask you, after this meeting, to do
Prime Minister: media reassurance around civilian infrastructure, civilians, reassurance about investigation of the F -35 pilot.
Home Secretary
Host
Host: Prime Minister also tasks his defence secretary with releasing comments about what the armed forces will be doing.
Prime Minister: rather crisp and factual, current defence statement about we have deployed what we've seen unprecedented sort of keywords, unprecedented deployments working with allies. So reassurance from defence, we have a plan from the Home Office, which I always think is important, to communicate you have a plan? Yes, that's the most important thing.
Prime Minister: think
National Security Advisor: you have to go, if I may, I think we all have our homework to do. Foreign secretary and I will start working with phones, we'll get you engaged as we need to. Thank you very much indeed. Break, break, break.
Games Master
Games Master: you.
Host: Rob Johnson ends the session in the Cobra room, though, the defence chief steps out and walks across the corridor
Host: a second room.
Host: Inside,
Host: the top operational commander has gathered a team of advisors to discuss the UK's limited options to defend itself.
Chief of Joint Operations
Host: General Sir David Capewell is a highly regarded and hugely experienced Royal Marines officer who spent almost four decades serving in the armed forces.
Host: He's reprising his former job as Chief of Joint Operations or CJAO.
Host: an emergency like this, he'd be an overall command of UK forces in the fight.
Chief of the Defence Staff: I've just come from Cobra,
Chief of the Defence Staff: it would be fair to say there's
Chief of the Defence Staff: quite a lot of disquiet of what's going on,
Chief of the Defence Staff: considerable uncertainty.
Chief of the Defence Staff: But I have some instructions, which we are going to have to tackle at speed.
Host: defence chief lists the tasks from defending the UK airspace to tracking the Russian Flotilla
Host: far too few jets, ships and missiles.
Chief of the Defence Staff: Everybody knows we can't do it all.
Host: He also says there's a big question mark over whether NATO is going to help.
Chief of Joint Operations: you, CDS.
Chief of Joint Operations: can definitely get on with the planning necessary to provide the
Chief of Joint Operations: protection and oversight and surveillance requirements that you've described.
Chief of Joint Operations: right at the back of my mind is that we are beginning to see the mortgageing of risk from political intent to operational reality. And the operational reality is that we are extremely thin on the ground and will require quite a lot of negotiation with NATO who will also be feeling the same pressure to do something nationally as opposed to collectively.
Chief of the Defence Staff
Chief of Joint Operations: So in the spirit
Chief of the Defence Staff: of the Cobra meeting, it was not the time for us to have a protective discussion about how we're dealing with a major Russian military threat,
Chief of the Defence Staff: armed forces that have been conditioned by 30 years of traveling through the post -Cole War era.
Chief of the Defence Staff: And we are where we are with what we have. And as you describe, unless NATO stands up and supports us now, we're going to feel
Chief of the Defence Staff: chilly pretty soon.
Host: then puts the crisis in even darker terms.
Chief of the Defence Staff: We want to be in a place where we're contributing to public reassurance, not public panic, and we're moving at speed.
Chief of the Defence Staff: To put it in another way, I can't tell you whether in 24 hours from now
Chief of the Defence Staff: are going to be
Chief of the Defence Staff: war with Russia,
Chief of the Defence Staff: you and I know that we don't have a plan for this.
Chief of the Defence Staff: We're massively under -resourced if we stand alone without NATO.
Chief of the Defence Staff: we haven't any time to fix this,
Chief of the Defence Staff: we're going to have to manage it.
Chief of Joint Operations: CDS, I'd like you to take one message back to
Chief of Joint Operations: Cabinet, please.
Chief of Joint Operations: If they think that we might have to start a fight, or certainly defend against a fight, what I want to be sure of is that they have a view about how we've finished this fight.
Host: up in episode two.
Host: afternoon.
Prime Minister: Good afternoon, Secretary General. We
Prime Minister: suffered a number of casualties.
Prime Minister: Russia's intention
Prime Minister: not just Britain, it is to fracture NATO.
Host: The war game was written and presented by me, Debra Hames.
Host: The series producer is James Shield.
Host: development producer is Jess Swimburn.
Host: Original music and sound design are by Tom Kinsella.
Host: Additional production by Katie Skulls.
Host: editor for Tortoise is Jasper Corbett.
Host: Sky News, the commissioning editor is Paul Stanworth.
Host: And the executive producers are Sarah Whitehead and David Mapstone.